<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life of that incomparable man, Faustus Socinus Senensis, described by a Polonian knight. Whereunto is added an excellent discourse, which the same author would have had premised to the works of Socinus; together with a catalogue of those works.</title>
            <title>Vita Fausti Socini Senensis. English</title>
            <author>Przypkowski, Samuel, 1592-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1489_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203303</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863292</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863292</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115484</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91323)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115484)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 191:E1489[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life of that incomparable man, Faustus Socinus Senensis, described by a Polonian knight. Whereunto is added an excellent discourse, which the same author would have had premised to the works of Socinus; together with a catalogue of those works.</title>
                  <title>Vita Fausti Socini Senensis. English</title>
                  <author>Przypkowski, Samuel, 1592-1670.</author>
                  <author>Biddle, John, 1615-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 35, [4], 38-61, [9] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Moone, at the seven Stars in Pauls Church-yard, neer the great north-doore.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A Polonian knight = Samuel Przypkowski.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Vita Fausti Socini Senensis.</note>
                  <note>Translator's note "To the reader" signed: J.B., i.e. John Biddle.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf bear printer's mark.</note>
                  <note>"An excellent discourse which the same Polonian knight would have had premised to the works of Socinus" has separate dated title page; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>The page before 38 is numbered 38.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June [the] 29: 1653".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Socinus, Faustus, 1539-1604.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:115484:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
THE LIFE OF THAT Incomparable Man, <hi>Fauſtus Socinus Senenſis,</hi> Deſcribed by a <hi>POLONIAN</hi> Knight. Whereunto is added.</p>
                  <p>An Excellent Diſcourſe, which the ſame Author would have had premiſed to the Works OF SOCINUS;</p>
                  <p>Together with a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of thoſe WORKS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Moone,</hi> at the ſeven Stars in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church yard, neer the great North-doore. 1653.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115484:2"/>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115484:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Life of <hi>Socinus</hi> is here expoſed to thy view, that by the peruſal ther of thou maiſt receive cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain information concerning the man, whom Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters &amp; others traduce by cuſtome, having (for the moſt part) never heard any thing of his converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor ſeen any of his works, or if they have, they were either unable or unwilling to make a thorow ſcrutiny into them, and ſo no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel if they ſpeak evil of him. To ſay any thing of him here by way
<pb facs="tcp:115484:3"/>
Elogy, as that he was one of the moſt pregnant wits that the world hath produced; that none ſince the Apoſtles hath deſerved better of our Religion, in that the Lord Chriſt hath chiefly made uſe of his Miniſtry to retrive ſo many preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous truths of the Goſpel, which had a long time been hidden from the eyes of men by the artifice of Satan; that he ſhewed the world a more accurate way to diſcuſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies in Religion, and to fetch out the very marrow of the Holy Scripture, ſo that a man may more availe himſelf by reading his works, then perhaps by peruſing all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, together with the writings of more modern Authors; that the vertues of his will were not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior unto thoſe of his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he being every way furniſhed to the work of the Lord; that he opened the right way to bring Chriſtians to the unity of the faith
<pb facs="tcp:115484:3"/>
and acknowledgement of the Son of God; that he took the ſame courſe to propagate the Goſpel, that Chriſt and the Apoſtles had done before him, forſaking his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and his neareſt relations, and undergoing all manner of labours and hazards, to draw men to the knowledge of the truth; that he had no other end of all his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, then the Glory of God and Chriſt, and the ſalvation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and others, it being impoſſible for Calumny it ſelf with any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to aſperſe him with the leaſt ſuſpicion of worldly intereſt; that he of all Interpreters explaineth the precepts of Chriſt in the ſtricteſt maner, and windeth up the lives of men to the higheſt ſtrain of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: to ſay theſe and other the like things (though in themſelves true and certain) would notwithſtanding here be impertinent, in that it would foreſtall what the Polonian Knight
<pb facs="tcp:115484:4"/>
hath written on this ſubject. To him therefore I refer thee, deſiring thee to read his words without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, and then the works of <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> himſelf; and though thou beeſt not thereby convinced that all which <hi>Socinus</hi> taught is true (for neither am I my ſelf of that belief, as having diſcovered that in ſome leſſer things <hi>Socinus,</hi> as a man, went awry, however in the main he hit the truth) yet for ſo much of Chriſt as thou muſt needs confeſs appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in him, begin to have more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable thoughts of him and his Followers.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I. B.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115484:4"/>
                  <head>THE LIFE OF <hi>Fauſtus Socinus Senenſis.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O purſue the Life of <hi>Fauſtus Socinus</hi> in a brief and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functory manner, would be below the dignity of ſo great a man; but to do it fully and elaborately, would perhaps be above our ſtrength. For to relate the praiſes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned men by ſnatches, and in a negligent faſhion, is an injury to vertue: and if there was ever any, certainly this is the man who deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be deſcribed not only with care, but alſo with wit. Yet ſince it is better that excellent endowments ſhould be commended below their merit; then wholly paſſed-over in ſilence: it is unreaſonable, either that the meanneſs of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115484:5"/>
ſhould prove prejudicial to famous men, or the greatneſs of thoſe who are celebrated be any prejudice to the wit of the Writers. But as for my ſelf, pardon is due to me upon another account, being cumbred with many cares, and hurrying my diſcourſe within the limits prefixed to a pittance of time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Socinus</hi> was born in <hi>Sene,</hi> a moſt famous City of <hi>Tuſcany.</hi> The Nobility of his ſtock was ancient, and the ſplendor of his Alliances exceeding the condition of a private man. His father, beſides the honors of his own Family, was on his mothers ſide further ennobled by the <hi>Salvetti.</hi> Which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily ſometimes flouriſhed with ſo great power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Florentines,</hi> that <hi>Pandulphus Petruccius</hi> being expelled out of <hi>Sene,</hi> was chiefly behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the aſſiſtance and wealth of <hi>Paulus Salvet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> for the reſtitution of his Country, and ſhortly after of his Princedome. By which benefit being obliged, he conferred on him the freedom of the City, and perſwaded him to leave his countrey and dwell at <hi>Sene.</hi> This <hi>Paulus</hi> was father to <hi>Camilla,</hi> who being marryed to <hi>Marianus</hi> the yonger, was mother to <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Laelius So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinus,</hi> and grandmother to <hi>Fauſtus.</hi> His mother, born to the hope of more then a private fortune, was daughter to <hi>Burgeſius Petruccius</hi> (ſometimes Prince of the Commonwealth of <hi>Sene)</hi> and to <hi>Victoria Piccolominea,</hi> who being the daughter of <hi>Andreas Piccolomineus,</hi> Lord of <hi>Caſtilio</hi> and <hi>Piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and Niece to Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond and third of that name, and either Siſter or Kinſwoman to Cardinal <hi>John Piccolomineus,</hi> to the Dukes of the <hi>Amalphitani,</hi> to the Marquiſſes of <hi>Capiſtranum,</hi> to the Earles of <hi>Calanum,</hi> and many other <hi>Italian</hi> Princes, marryed into the houſe of the <hi>Petruccii,</hi>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115484:5"/>
which then held the Fortune of the Princedome of <hi>Sene.</hi> But <hi>Burgeſius</hi> ſucceeding his father <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulphus,</hi> and not long after by a fatal change ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled out of his countrey, did not long ſurvive his dignity. Nevertheleſs Cardinal <hi>Raphael Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truccius</hi> was his ſucceſſor in the Government of his countrey, and held for a while the helm of that Commonwealth. But <hi>Victoria,</hi> being left a widow, ſuffered not her mind, which in the ſplendor of her former height ſhe had never lifted-up, to be quailed with ſo diſaſtrous a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitude of things. So that for the ſpace of fifty ſix yeers, wherein ſhe ſurvived the life and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fortune of her husband, ſhe did with ſingular modeſty, and approved integrity and chaſtity, endure the ſolitary condition of widowhood. Her daughter <hi>Agnes,</hi> whom according to the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſo great a family, ſhe had trained up in moſt holy manners, ſhe gave in marriage to <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Socinus,</hi> a young man of noble extraction, but private condition. He was the Father of our <hi>Faustus,</hi> and born in ſuch a family as had for a long time, not by Arms and Power, but by wit and Scholarſhip, ſeemed to hold a kind of Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in one ſort of learning. For this very <hi>Alexander</hi> was called the maſter of ſubtilties; and his Father <hi>Marianus</hi> the younger, the Prince of Lawyers; and <hi>Bartholmew</hi> the Un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kle of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianus</hi> the younger, was by <hi>Angelus Politianus</hi> ſtiled the <hi>Papinian</hi> of his age; finally <hi>Marianus</hi> the elder, <hi>Bartholmews</hi> father, a moſt grave Lawyer, is by <hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi> ſo highly extolled, that that the narration almoſt exceeds belief.</p>
                  <p>The ſon of this <hi>Marianus</hi> was <hi>Alexander</hi> the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; the grandchild, <hi>Marianus</hi> the yonger; the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115484:6"/>
Great-grandchildren, <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Laelius,</hi> the one, (as we ſaid) the father; the other, the Unkle of our <hi>Fauſtus.</hi> Both of them for great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of wit, and endowments of Learning, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding famous, but to whom that of the Poet may juſtly be applyed,</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Theſe to the earth the Fates will only ſhow,</l>
                     <l>Cauſing them preſently away to go.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>For <hi>Alexander,</hi> having a marvellous ſharpneſs of wit, together with a Divine memory and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Eloquence, had ſcarce fulfilled the one and thirtieth yeer of his age, but he was ſuddenly ſnatched away, to the great grief of all <hi>Italy.</hi> And <hi>Laelius</hi> having in a ſhort race of life perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very great matters, exceeded not the ſeven and thirtieth yeer of his age.</p>
                  <p>The memory of this man I judge worthy to be exceedingly admired by poſterity, who in ſo ſhort a ſpace as he lived, not only ſmelt-out ſo many grievous errors, which had privily crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church; but pulling them out of their very holes, firſt ſhewed the way how to kill them. He being by his Father <hi>Marianus</hi> put upon that ſtudy which was hereditary to his name, thought that the knowledge of humane Laws was to be ſetched out of the very fountains of Gods Law. To which purpoſe whilſt he diligently turned-over the ſacred volumes, he without difficulty found that very many of thoſe Doctrines of the Church, which are commonly received, are quite oppoſite to the Divine Teſtimonies. And that ſo much the more eaſily, becauſe moſt of them are alſo repugnant to Reaſon, and ſuch principles, as Nature it ſelf hath implanted in us. Inaſmuch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115484:6"/>
therefore as the height of his excellent wit and ſharpneſs of his judgement was accompanyed with a ſingular probity of mind, having detected the errors of the Church, he did not (as the greateſt part do) abuſe them to the contempt of the Scripture and Religion; but rather uſed the authority of the Scripture and of the Chriſtian Religion to heal the diſeaſes of the Church, which could not be cured, unleſs the errors were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected. Wherefore in that ſtudy, to which his ſublime and pious mind was carryed with inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpeed, a great light, not without the Divine Aſſiſtance, ſuddenly brake out unto him, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe to fetch out the ſenſes of the Scripture, he brought with him the knowledge of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ental Tongues, the Hebrew and Greek chiefly, and alſo the Arabick. Whether therefore it were for fear of danger, (as it is likely) or that he might more exactly ſtudy purer Divinity and the Tongues, he ſoon paſſed out of <hi>Italy</hi> into <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland</hi> and <hi>Germany.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He left his country very young, not being above one and twenty yeeers old. In the next four yeers, having travelled over <hi>France, Britanny, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium,</hi> all <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> he took up his dwelling at <hi>Zurich.</hi> Whereupon, although he were often drawn away with publicke and private affairs, yet did he ſpend the chiefeſt part of his exile there, being endeared to ſundry Princes in all parts, and favoured alſo by certain Kings.</p>
                  <p>There was not a noted Scholar in that time, (then which none ever abounded more with learned men,) but he had by his carriage won not onely his friendſhip, but his ſamiliarity alſo. Whereby it came to paſs, that the inbred good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115484:7"/>
of his judgement was accompanyed with a ſingular prudence and ſweetneſs of behaviour. Which endowments are acknowledged in him as by very many other famous men, ſo chiefly by <hi>Philip Melanchton</hi> in his commendatory Letters which he wrote to him as he was departing. And indeed what correſpondence was between him and the moſt renowned men of that age, chiefly <hi>Calvin, Melanchthon, Bullinger, Brentius, Muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Munſter, Zanchius, Vergerius, Caſtellio, Beza, Martyr, Ochinus, Coeleus,</hi> and ſundry others, their frequent Letters unto him do teſtifie, the coppies whereof in a great number have come to our hands. He did not more deſire to enjoy their friendſhip for the ſafe-guard of his fortune, then to make uſe of the ſame to the benefit of the Church. Wherefore he did by his queſtions much urge and exerciſe thoſe redoubted Doctors of then-flouriſhing Divinty. I have a Letter written with <hi>Calvins</hi> own hand, wherein he open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſeth that he was put into choler by him, and in ſtead of an anſwer ſends him back a check and threatning.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is not fit,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that you ſhould expect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till I anſwer thoſe portentous queſtions which you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. If you are diſpoſed to fly through thoſe aiery ſpeculations, I beſeech you, ſuffer me, an bumble Diſciple of Chriſt, to meditate on ſuch things, as tend to the edification of my faith. And indeed I will by my ſilence gain what I deſire, nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ly that you be not henceforth troubleſome to me. Now that ſo gallant a wit, as the Lord hath beſtowed on you, ſhould not only be unprofitably taken-up with ſlight matters, but alſo corrupted with pernicious figments, is a very</hi>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115484:7"/>
                        <hi>great grief. What I not long ſince teſtified, I again ſeriouſly warn you of: that if you do not timouſly correct this itch of enquiring, it is to be feared, you will draw on your ſelf great torments. Should I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſhew of indulgence cheriſh ſuch a vice as I know to be very hurtful, I ſhould be perfidious and cruel towards you. Wherefore I had either you ſhould be a little offended with my roughneſs, then be drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the ſweet allurements of curioſity beyond all recovery. The time will come, I hope, when you will rejoyce that you were ſo boiſterouſly awakened.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Jan. 1. 1552.</p>
                     <p>Yours, John Calvin.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Neither was the truth of his threatning either uncertain or contemptible: For in the moneth of <hi>October</hi> the next yeer <hi>Servetus</hi> was burned at <hi>Geneva.</hi> Nevertheleſs the gravity of <hi>Laelius,</hi> and his incredible modeſty in the greateſt endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of learning and wit, together with his dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity of carriage, had ſo diſarmed the anger of thoſe that were in a chafe, that they did not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to hate the man, although otherwiſe they could not brook his freedome. Which thing may teach them, whom over-much freedom of truth betrayeth into needleſs dangers, that that very Truth which they maintain, is more ſecured by the circumſpect mildneſs of prudence, then by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled zeal. So that they who of their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord meet dangers, ſeem to make greater haſt to their own praiſe, then to the advancement of the publike good. And certainly if there be any, this is the place where the ſimplicity of the Dove is to be mingled with the ſubtilty of the Serpent:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115484:8"/>
unleſs we ſuſpect the counſel of our Saviour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning their unadviſed raſhneſs, who oftentimes have very bad ſucceſs in caſting-down their pearles where they cannot be eſtimated accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their worth. The truth is, <hi>Laelius</hi> remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed entire and inviolate amongſt the capital ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his opinion. Yet did he not ſuffer the ſenſe of his judgement to periſh within the cloſet of his conſcience. Wherefore to thoſe whom he liked, he feared not to entruſt the things that had been diſcovered to him by God. But chiefly he inſtructed his countrey-men the <hi>Italians,</hi> who by a pious and voluntary exile were ſcattered through ſeveral regions of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Poland.</hi> I finde in the commentaries of the <hi>Polonian</hi> Churches, that he came twice into our countrey. Firſt, about the yeer 1551. when he was ſix and twenty yeers old. At what time he is ſaid not without great ſucceſs to have converſed with very many of the <hi>Polonian</hi> Nobility; and to have cauſed <hi>Francis Liſmaninus</hi> the <hi>Corcyraean,</hi> confeſſor to <hi>Bona Sforzia</hi> the Queen, and who was then (if I be not miſtaken) the provincial of the Minorites, and firſt lifted up an enſigne of revolt from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ope in this kingdome, to caſt away his Cowle. But then in a few moneths ſpace departing into <hi>Moravia,</hi> he reti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d thence to the <hi>Switzers.</hi> His ſecond coming into <hi>Poland</hi> I find to have happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after the death of his father <hi>Marianus,</hi> who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Bononia</hi> in the yeer 1556. For not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, about the yeers 1558 and 1559 he deſired letters of recommendation from the Kings of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> that he might the more ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treat with his friends in <hi>Venice</hi> concerning his Patrimony. Then indeed it appeared to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115484:8"/>
greateſt part of the <hi>German</hi> and <hi>Polonian</hi> Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in what favour he was. For in his caſe there was very great canvaſſing both with <hi>Lud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vicus Priulus</hi> the Doge of <hi>Venice,</hi> and <hi>Coſmus</hi> the grand Duke of <hi>Tuſcany.</hi> Almoſt about the ſame time a grievous ſtorm ariſing upon a ſuſpicion of Hereſy, did with a perillous guſt ſhake the whole Houſe of the <hi>Socini.</hi> After the death of <hi>Alexander, Lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> had three brethren ſurviving: of whom <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> lived at <hi>Bononia, Cornelius</hi> and <hi>Camillus</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> ſon to his brother <hi>Alexander,</hi> dwelt at <hi>Sene.</hi> Amongſt theſe alſo <hi>Laelius,</hi> a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Artiſt in ſuggeſting the truth, had ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the ſeeds thereof, and though he were ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the remote diſtances of countries, yet did he by effectual induſtry ſo cheriſh them, that being unknown as yet, and abſent, he drew the wives of ſome to his party. Nor were there wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting amongſt his other familiars and friends, ſuch as were either partners in the ſame deſigne, or privy thereunto. But the fair hope of that crop was blaſted in the very blade, <hi>Cornelius</hi> being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and the reſt either ſcattered, or chaſed away. This fear drave <hi>Fauſtus</hi> alſo, then very yong, not only out of his native City, but out of <hi>Italy,</hi> it ſelf. Who having lived a while at <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>Franc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, Laelius</hi> was in the mean time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xtinguiſhed by an untimely death at <hi>Zurich. Fauſtus</hi> being certified of his death by the letters of <hi>Marius Beſozzus,</hi> had much ado to prevent the ſnares laid for his papers, yet got the poſſeſſion thereof, having been already by him informed of very many things, which he afterwards in long progreſs of time did by his ſharp wit and indefatigable ſtudy poliſh. The death of <hi>Laelius</hi> happened on the third day
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115484:9"/>
after the Ides of <hi>May</hi> 1562 &amp; in the thirty ſeventh yeer of his age. That ſo great a wit was not long-lived, will not ſeem ſtrange to him who ſhall conſider how ſoon it was ripe. He had hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſt the age of a ſtripling when he left <hi>Italy.</hi> Within the ſix and twentieth yeer of his life, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing travelled almoſt through all the regions of the Weſt, he was by his great renown made known to moſt of the chief Nobility in ſundry parts, and perhaps to all learned men every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. It was well-nigh fifteen yeers that he was abſent from his countrey. Out of ſo ſmall a ſpace of life far journeys challenge a great part, by means of which his exile became profitable to many in ſundry coaſts of <hi>Europe.</hi> Adde his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual commerce with ſo many great men, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his continual intercourſe of letters, and when you have ſubtracted theſe things, how ſmall a pittance of time (I pray you) was left for his ſtudyes? And now being amazed, we muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, what was that ſo profound leaſure? what ſo vigorous induſtry? what ſo ready wit? what ſo vaſt underſtanding, as was ſufficient to maſter ſo many tongues, ſo many ſciences, and withall to recollect the minde to it ſelf, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the greateſt affairs? To premiſe theſe things touching <hi>Laelius,</hi> had I not liſted of my own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, neceſſity it ſelf did require. For he it was who by his guidance and counſel drew <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> himſelf and others to enter into that way, which they afterwards followed.</p>
                  <p>Now I return to <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> intending in the firſt place to relate in brief the courſe and chief oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences of his life; then to compriſe his chief actions; and laſtly to add a few words concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115484:9"/>
the habit of his mind and body, as far as I have by a curſory enquiry attained the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof.</p>
                  <p>He was born two hours and almoſt three quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters before Sun-riſing on the Nones of <hi>December,</hi> 1539, well-nigh fourteen yeers yonger then his Unkle <hi>Laelius.</hi> He dyed in the yeer 1604, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before the beginning of the ſpring, being ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty five yeers old.</p>
                  <p>He firſt ſpent twenty, and a little after twelve yeers of his age in his countrey; about three in his retirement at <hi>Lyons;</hi> the other thirty in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary exile. He ſeemeth to have loſt his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents at that age, which is moſt apt for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of learning and wit. For he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth how he employed his labor in the ſtudys of good arts very ſlightly, and without the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of a teacher. And elſwhere, how he had not learnt Philoſophy, nor ever was acquainted with School-divinity; and confeſſeth that in Logick it ſelf he never taſted but only certain rudiments, and that very late.</p>
                  <p>It was a baſſle to that proud age, to be taught by ſo notable an inſtance, that even without thoſe helps (which we, though not without cauſe, yet oftentimes without meaſure do admire) there may be great men, and ſuch as will perform rare feats. Perhaps alſo it was expedient, that a wit born to take cogniſance of the Opinions of the world, ſhould be tainted with no prejudices; leſt it ſhould admit ſome ſtring of thoſe errours, for the rooting out of which it grew up. For Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity being full of errors, infected alſo Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy it ſelf, and almoſt all good arts. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not only in the cradle, but alſo in the very
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115484:10"/>
rudiments of the firſt learning the infancy of the world hath now for a long time been deceived, and ſucked in opinions as true, before it was able to judge whether they were falſe. Whereby it cometh to paſs, that oftentimes it is better to be ſeaſoned with none, then with perverſe doctrines: nor is it a wonder that ſometimes learned men dote more ſhamefully, and the rude multitude judgeth more ſincerely. Which I would not have ſo taken, as if I would condemn learning, but only the abuſe thereof; nor give a check, but a caution to it. With ſuch a ſlight tincture of learning, and (as I ſuppoſe) with the ſtudy of the Civil law, the firſt age of <hi>Socinus</hi> was taken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up, untill the three and twentieth yeer. Yet had he before ſucked-in the principles of Divine Truth, partly by his own ſharp wit, partly by the inſtruction of his Unkle <hi>Laelius,</hi> eſpecially when upon the riſing of a ſudden tempeſt, he, as we before hinted, betook himſelf into <hi>France.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Laelius,</hi> confiding in the wit of his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, did intimate more to his gueſs, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver to his underſtanding; concealing alſo ſome things from the yong man for the tryal of his judgement, and openly preſaging amongſt his friends, that theſe things ſhould more fully and happily by <hi>Fauſtus</hi> be diſcovered to the world. But when after the death of <hi>Laelius</hi> he was return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into <hi>Italy,</hi> in that unſteddy age of his life, his youth floating like a ſhip without a Pilot, and carryed away with I know not what winds, almoſt grew old amongſt the <hi>Sirens</hi> of the Court. For being admitted into the Palace of <hi>Francis</hi> the grand Duk of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> and very much endeared to him by honourable employments, whileſt he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115484:10"/>
there flouriſhed in higheſt favour and dignity, he ſpent whole twelve yeers in the Court of <hi>Florence.</hi> Then did he loſe (as he with perpetual grones complained) the moſt flouriſhing part of his life; if at leaſt that time is to be accounted loſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his ſublime judgement was formed, not with the ſhadowy precepts of Learning, but with the ſubſtantial experiments of Life; wherein alſo that youthful heat of his evaporated, which for the moſt part hurryeth great wits to great falls. And indeed, were we not otherwiſe aſſured of it, yet from the very force of his wit we might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture with how vehement motions that nature of his was ſometimes agitated. About the cloſe of that time his heart was touched with a ſerious deliberation concerning the choice of good things; which he performed with ſuch greatneſs of minde, that he determined for the hope of heavenly things to trample under foot all the commodityes of earthly wiſhes; wherefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay, deſpairing to obtain from the extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unwilling Princes leave to depart, he of his own accord forſook his countrey, friends, hopes and riches, that he might the more freely employ himſelf about his own and other mens ſalvation. That his ſervice had not been ungrateful to the Grand Duke, the longing after him being now abſent and in exile, ſhewed. For ſundry times by letters and meſſengers, chiefly at the motion of <hi>Paulus Jordanus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus</hi> a noble man, who had marryed the Grand Dukes ſiſter, he ſollicited <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinus</hi> to return, which he with uſual modeſty, but reſolute mind did refuſe. It was the yeer of our Lord 1574, and the five and thirtieth of his age, when he retired out of <hi>Italy</hi> into <hi>Germany.</hi> At
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115484:11"/>
his coming he was entertained by <hi>Baſile,</hi> that cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous receiver of Chriſt's exiles, which had long ſince learned to cheriſh in her lap endangered Innocency. Where he ſtudyed Divinity full three yeers and upwards, being chiefly intent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sacred Scriptures, to the ſincere under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding whereof whileſt he aſpired with daily vows and prayers, he was much helped with a very few writings of his Unkle <hi>Laelius,</hi> and ſundry ſcattered notes left by him. Which thing, though it was in his power to ſuppreſs it, yet did he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ingenuouſly own and profeſs. As he lived at <hi>Baſile</hi> untill the yeer 1575, he detained not within the cloſet of his private breaſt, the truth that had been depoſited with him. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whileſt he endeavoureth to propagate unto others the light that was riſen to himſelf, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by degrees from reaſoning with his friends to diſcourſe with ſtrangers, and having begun his diſputation <hi>concerning Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour</hi> by word of mouth, he afterwards compriſed it in writing. Which ere he could finiſh, being firſt excluded by ſickneſs from his ſtudyes, then by the peſtilence from his books left at <hi>Baſile,</hi> he in the mean time diſpatched at <hi>Zurich,</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the yeer 1578 another Diſputation with <hi>Franciſcus Puccius;</hi> and afterwards in the ſame yeer being returned to <hi>Baſile,</hi> he put the laſt hand to his book <hi>concerning the Saviour.</hi> At that time the <hi>Tranſyivanian</hi> Churches were extremely infeſted with the opinion of <hi>Franciſcus Davidis</hi> and others touching the Honour and Power of Chriſt. To remedy which miſchief, <hi>Georgius Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a</hi> (a man very powerful in thoſe Churche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and with the <hi>Bath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Princes</hi> who then ruled the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115484:11"/>
in that very yeer of the Lord invited <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> from <hi>Baſile,</hi> to the end he might draw the Ringleader of the Faction, <hi>Franciſcus Davidis,</hi> from ſo groſs and pernicious an error. Which that it might the more commodiouſly be effected, having at a great rate hired a lodging for <hi>Socinus,</hi> with <hi>Franciſcus Davidis,</hi> he would have them both for above the ſpace of four moneths to uſe the ſame houſe and table. But the ſaid <hi>Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> took far greater care how to retain his credit amongſt thoſe of his party, then how to ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the truth. Whereupon adventuring not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſpread his error in private, but publikely to proclaim it in the Pulpit, lie drew preſent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger on himſelf, being ſoon caſt into priſon by the command of the Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> where he ſhortly after ended his life. Of whoſe death though <hi>Socinus</hi> was altogether guiltleſs, yet did he not eſcape blame. As if he were not able to vanquiſh the ſaid <hi>Franciſcus</hi> with other weapons, when notwithſtanding the diſputations of both are publiſhed: or that Magiſtrate was ſo addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the cauſe of <hi>Socinus,</hi> as to employ the weap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his authority for him or any one of his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But if perhaps ſome perſon, who ſavored the cauſe of <hi>Socinus,</hi> did incite the Prince to deal roughly with the ſaid <hi>Franciſcus,</hi> (whereof never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs I am not certain,) yet let not <hi>Socinus</hi> be blamed for him, inaſmuch as he could neither know his counſel, nor approve his deed. For to omit ſundry other conſiderations, there could not happen any thing more contrary to the mind of <hi>Socinus,</hi> then that ſuch a doctrine, as could not be defended with the words and wit of the ſaid <hi>Franciſcus</hi> whileſt he lived, ſhould ſeem to be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115484:12"/>
confirmed by the mute, but efficacious teſtimony of his death: eſpecially becauſe, carrying the face of a Martyrdome, it preſently turned the eyes of all men to it. The Diſputation of <hi>Seci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> with him, though written whileſt the ſaid <hi>Franciſcus</hi> was alive, could notwithſtanding hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to light fifteen yeers after. When this Diſputation was finiſhed in <hi>May,</hi> anno 1579, and preſented to the <hi>Tranſylvanian</hi> Churches, <hi>Socinus</hi> could not long tarry there, by reaſon of a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe then raging, which they commonly call the Colick. Wherefore in the ſame yeer, being now forty yeers old, he travelled into <hi>Poland,</hi> where he made ſuit publikely to be united to the <hi>Poloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Churches, which acknowledge none but the Father of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to be the moſt High God: but not concealing his diſſent in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain doctrines, here ſuffered a repulſe very rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and for a long time.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs he, being compoſed unto pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence not ſo much by his natural inclination, as by the reſolution of his mind, was no whit enraged with this diſgrace, nor ever gave any ſignes of a diſaffected mind; But rather undertook to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell with his wit the incurſion of divers Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaryes, who then infeſted thoſe Churches. And firſt of all he received the charge of <hi>Andreas Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus,</hi> by refelling his <hi>Paraeneſis;</hi> and upon the ſame occaſion, at the requeſt of <hi>Niemojevius</hi> the ſeventh Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> was explained. Afterwards it pleaſed him to aſſail <hi>Jacobus Palaeologus,</hi> whoſe reputation and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity did at that time cheriſh the relicks of pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous errors in men otherwiſe well-minded. Him being ſomewhat roughly handled, not out of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115484:12"/>
hatred, but advice, he alwayes excuſed. A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after, when <hi>Volanus</hi> had renewed the fight, he was again encountred, and withall an Anſwer made to the Poſitions of the College of <hi>Ponſa.</hi> Whileſt <hi>Socinus</hi> undergoeth ſo much fighting and hatred for the patronage of the truth, amongſt ſo many enemies there wanted not ſome Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niators. <hi>Stephanus</hi> was then King of <hi>Poland.</hi> A Pickthank blows his ears with the report of a book written againſt the Magiſtrate; adding that it would be a very diſhonorable thing to ſuffer a wandring <hi>Italian</hi> exile to eſcape ſcotfree with ſo bold an enterpriſe. He hinted at the book againſt <hi>Palaeologus.</hi> Which though it required no other teſtimony of its innocency, then the reading, yet did he think good to decline the danger.</p>
                  <p>Whereupon he departed from Cracovia, where he had now lived four yeers, to a Noble man, named <hi>Chriſtophorus Morſtinus,</hi> Lord of <hi>Pawlico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> in which place he defended his innocency not ſo much by skulking, as by the Privilege of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility in our Nation. For that ſuburb-farm is a few miles diſtant from Cracovia. It ſeemed a wiſer courſe to cleer himſelf from the crimes laid to his charge, rather out of that place, then out of priſon. Nor was he entertained in that hoſpitable houſe for that nick of time onely, but there cheriſhed for above three yeers. And to the end that the curteſie ſhewed to an exile and ſtranger might be more abundant, a little while after the daughter of the family, a noble Virgin, was at his ſuit given him in marriage; ſo that being of a ſtranger become a ſon-in-law, he ſeemed to have eſtabliſhed his ſecurity in thoſe places by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115484:13"/>
affinities and friendſhips. Whileſt he lived in the countrey, he wrote many notable pieces, and chiefly that againſt <hi>Eutropius,</hi> conſtantly defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fame and cauſe of that Church, which had with moſt unjuſt prejudice condemned him, and cauſed him, though innocent, continually to ſuffer many indignityes. His daughter <hi>Agnes</hi> was born to him in the yeer of our Lord 1587, and forty eighth of his age, of whom, being after her fathers death marryed to <hi>Staniſlaus Wiſzowatius</hi> a <hi>Polonian</hi> Knight, there are as yet remaining nephews and nieces. In <hi>September</hi> the ſame yeer he loſt his wife <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which ſad and diſaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous chance was followed with a grievour fit of bodily ſickneſs, ſo obſtinate, that for certain moneths it cauſed the uſe of his ſtudyes to ceaſe. And that no kind of calamity might be wanting, almoſt about the ſame time, by the death of <hi>Franciſcus</hi> the Grand Duke of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of his eſtate, which he received yeerly out of Italy, were quite taken away from him. Indeed a little before, by the bitterneſs of Accuſers, and threats of Popes, his eſtate came into danger. But by the ſtrenuous endeavour of <hi>Iſabella Medicea</hi> the Grand Dukes ſiſter, (who was marryed to the aforeſaid <hi>Paulus Jordanus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus,)</hi> whileſt ſhe lived, and afterwards by the favour of <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus</hi> the Grand Duke, it came to paſs that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his life <hi>Socinus</hi> received the yeerly income of his eſtate. For indeed his old deſerts were ſtill ſo freſh in memory, that thoſe Princes though long ſince forſaken, and oftentimes rejected, did yet in a moſt difficult matter gratifie the letters and prayers of a condemned and exiled perſon. Yea letters full of curteſie were ſent unto him,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115484:13"/>
and he bidden to be of good chear for the future, as long as they lived, ſo that in ſetting forth books he ſuffered not his name to appear. But thoſe Princes were then taken away by a deſtiny diſaſtrous to <hi>Socinus.</hi> And that all things might ſeem to have conſpired to the perplexity of the man, being a widower, ſick, and ſtripped of all his fortunes, he was moleſted with the very times of our Commonwealth, which were then exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing turbulent, becauſe divers did contend who ſhould be the King of <hi>Poland;</hi> ſo that the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaryes thereupon took greater licenſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>Socinus</hi> was now returned to <hi>Cracovia,</hi> and ſought ſolace in the midſt of ſo many evils from the employment which God had impoſed on him, to purge the Church of ſuch errors, as were then rife in her. Wherefore although he had been formerly accuſtomed to frequent Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Aſſemblies, yet in the yeer 1588 in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of <hi>Breſte</hi> (which is a Town on the borders of <hi>Lituania)</hi> he diſputed with greater earneſtneſs and fruit then before touching the death and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Chriſt, touching our Juſtification, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Corrupted Nature of Man, and finally with the <hi>Davidians</hi> and <hi>Budneiſts</hi> touching the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Jeſus Chriſt. This was the yeer wherein the care and charge of the Church at <hi>Luclavicia</hi> was committed to <hi>Petrus Sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nius,</hi> ſon to <hi>Petrus Statoriu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> of <hi>Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ville,</hi> whoſe family ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heretofore been naturaliſed into the Nobili-of our Nation, hath even at this day ſome men ſurviving who have been inveſted with great Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors in our countrey. He being no leſs ſharp in judgement, then ready in ſpeech, being once admitted into the friendſhip of <hi>Socinus,</hi> yielded
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115484:14"/>
willingly to his Opinion. A little before alſo he had privately drawn many of the chief ones into his Opinion, and there was daily an acceſſion made of ſuch men as complyed with them. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs certain men of very great authority ſtill ſtood off, as <hi>Niemojevius,</hi> and <hi>Czechovicius,</hi> together with the greateſt part of the ancient Miniſters. The report is that <hi>Securinius</hi> was the firſt that adventured openly to maintain the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets of <hi>Socinus,</hi> to which he had aſſented. Not long after others followed. Which party was exceedingly ſtrengthened by the acceſſion of the three <hi>Lubjenecii, Andreas, Staniſlaus,</hi> and <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus,</hi> who being brethren of noble deſcent, and born to very great hopes, and brought up partly in the Kings Court, partly in the ſociety of the greateſt Peers, were by a ſacred inſtinct tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported from the midſt of the allurements of this life to the care of Religion. Theſe men, as they had by a moſt enflamed zeal trodden under foot all the impediments of piety, ſo with an equal candor and greatneſs of mind they ſubſcribed to the known Truth.</p>
                  <p>And now others of the paſtors came-in a vye to the party, eſpecially the juniors, who were leſs retarded with the prejudice of inveterate opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and authority, and that by reaſon of an accident very notable for the newneſs thereof, which gave a memorable proof how great the force of the Truth is. Amidſt a great jarring of Opinions this was a laudable agreement of that Church, that thoſe men contended only with ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and not with hatred. And though they deteſted one anothers opinions, yet did they not condemne one another. And therefore keeping
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115484:14"/>
mutual tolerance entire, they oftentimes diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted very eagerly, and this was the chief work of their Synods.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore anno 1585 in the Synod of <hi>Lublin,</hi> the opinion of <hi>Socinus</hi> touching the ſeventh Chap. of the <hi>Romans</hi> was exceedingly agitated. There were ſome that defended it; but as great a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Paſtors that oppoſed it. One whereof, named <hi>Nicolaus Zilinius,</hi> being willed by others of the ſame party to explain that Chapter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the mind of <hi>Socinus,</hi> and having to that purpoſe ſtoutly managed the matter, falling in his diſcourſe upon thoſe words, wherewith the Apoſtle giveth thanks to God for his freedome, ſtood like a man amazed. And by and by, what is that freedome? ſaith he. What is that bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, which drew from the Apoſtle ſo great thanks? was it, that he was of neceſſity detained in ſo great a ſervitude of ſin? Certainly ſuch a thing as this can at no hand gain approbation with me. I therefore (ſaith he) in like manner give very great thanks to the Father of lights, in that he would have the light of his truth ariſe unto me, who am now freed from error. Afterwards en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering upon a contrary way of explaining, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curately diſputed for the Orthodox Opinion. When they, whoſe cauſe he had undertaken, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amazed did rebuke him, his anſwer was, that he could not reſiſt the judgement of a convinced mind. This buſineſs was of great moment for the propagation of the Truth; nor did their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours leſs conduce thereunto, who had lifted up the ſtandard unto others to embrace it. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them the Eloquence of the foreſaid <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Stoinius</hi> did excell. That Elegant Tongue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115484:15"/>
only had God beſtowed on thoſe Churches equal to the wit of <hi>Socinus</hi> and able to deliver in a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular manner his ſubtile ſenſes that were above the capacity of the ruder ſort, and to commend them unto all by the genius of his flexanimous ſpeech. Him therefore, as the chief Interpreter of his mind, did <hi>Socinus</hi> make uſe of, to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table advantage of Gods Church. And indeed certain things happened, which did enforce a ſtricter union with him. <hi>Socinus</hi> ſojourning at <hi>Cracovia</hi> began long ſince to be environed with ſuch dangers on every ſide, as are for the moſt part wont to accompany the faithful ſervants of Chriſt. How great an Indignity was there offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him by that inſolent ſoldier <hi>Vernecus,</hi> he himſelf ſignifieth in a certain letter. But above all, after the printing of his book <hi>touching the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> the Adverſaryes again began to ſhew the rancor of their hatred. Whereupon in the yeer 1598 the Scholars, having ſtirred up the dregs of the rabble, took <hi>Socinus</hi> being then ſick and mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the recovery of his health, and pulling him out of his chamber half-naked, drag him in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious manner through the market and the the moſt noted ſtreets, the greateſt part in the mean time crying out to have him brought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution. At length having been grievouſly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in that furious rout, he was with much adoe reſcued out of the hands of the raging multitude by <hi>Martinus Vadovita</hi> Profeſſor of <hi>Cracovia.</hi> The plundering of his goods and houſhold-ſtuff, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with other things lyable to ſpoile, did not ſo much grieve him, as the irreparable loſs of certain writings, concerning which he often did profeſs that he would redeem it with the expenſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115484:15"/>
of his life. Then periſhed together a notable la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor of his againſt Atheiſts, which he had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to refute the ingenious Devices of a certain Great Man. But when to ſo barbarous an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of cruelty threats were alſo added, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>Cracovia</hi> to <hi>Luclavicia,</hi> unto a certain village famous for his laſt habitation and death, and diſtant about nine miles from <hi>Cracovia;</hi> where having for certain yeers uſed the table and houſe of a Noble Man, named <hi>Abrahamus Blonſcius,</hi> he lived a neighbor to <hi>Sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nius.</hi> Both therefore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording mutual help neer at hand in chaſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the relicks of errors, had now brought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt that whole Church to an unanimous conſent in all opinions: for even <hi>Niemojevius</hi> himſelf having in moſt things already given aſſent to <hi>Socinus,</hi> condemned his own miſtakes with ſuch ingenuity as can never ſufficiently be extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Czechovicius</hi> only could not be removed from his opinion. Who, as the better part prevailed, conniving, though with much adoe, at other things, a little after began to make a ſtir about the opinion concerning Baptiſm, which neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs being ſuddenly according to the wiſh of <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> laid aſleep, did afterwards vaniſh of its own accord. Having thus fully purged the Church from errors, as if his life had been prolonged hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto for this purpoſe only, he was at the end of winter, in the ſixty fifth yeer of his age taken away at <hi>Luclavicia,</hi> by a death not ſo untimely to himſelf, as ſad to his followers. His laſt words at his death were theſe, namely that he no leſs full of envy and troubles then of dayes, did with a joyful and undanted hope incline to the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115484:16"/>
period of his appointed time, which ſhewed to him both a diſcharge from his ſorrows and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his labours.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Petrus Stoinius</hi> who had been the aſſociate of his life and labours, was alſo the Praiſer, and in the yeer following the companion of his funeral. For as if he had already ended the appointed task of his life, he followed <hi>Socinus</hi> being hardly forty yeers old.</p>
                  <p>Having paſſed over the race of <hi>Socinus</hi> life, through which we have made a ſhort cut, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth that we ſtop a while in conſidering what he did, and performed.</p>
                  <p>No man in our memory did better deſerve of all the Chriſtian world, but chiefly of the <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Churches. For firſt, by ſetting out ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny works, he opened the genuine meaning of the Holy Scriptures in innumerable places.</p>
                  <p>Next, he only ſhewed how to confirm with ſolid arguments, and skilfully to defend from ſubtill cavills and ſophiſms, thoſe opinions touching the Perſon of God and Chriſt, which he found al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready rife in <hi>Poland.</hi> After that he happily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed ſome impious, other prophane opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whoſe deadly poiſon did by ſtealth inſinuate it ſelf into the boſome of the Church. No man did more vigorouſly quell <hi>Judaizers:</hi> he alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded the opinion of the <hi>Chiliaſts,</hi> and many other fanatick dreams beſides. As for the errors, received from the Reformed Churches, which did in a great number as yet raign in that Church, he did with a marvellous felicity root them out. Such were that of Juſtification, that of Appeaſing the wrath of God, that of Predeſtination, that of the Servitude of the Will, that of Original
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115484:16"/>
Sin, that of the Lords Supper and Baptiſm, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with other miſconſtrued Doctrines. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, having taken-away pernicious errors, that he might not alſo leave any fopperyes in the Church, he exterminated very many ſuperſtitions about indifferent things. Of which ſort was the over-much affectation of mean clothing, and the eſchewing of Magiſtracy, and refuſing to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ones own right even without a deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and what other like ſpots there were, cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the inconſiderate zeal of their firſt ſervor.</p>
                  <p>Having explained the order of his life, and his actions, it remaineth that we adde a few things concerning the habit of his Mind and Body. To relate the praiſes of his wit and judgement, is a ſuperfluous labour, inaſmuch as there are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny monuments thereof extant. As for his learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the more pertinaciouſly he hid it, the more impatiently it breaketh-out. It was ſomewhat late, but more ſolid. Nor are there wanting in his writings the footſteps of a happy memory alſo. I cannot paſs-by one proof thereof, which he gave in his diſputation with <hi>Chriſtianus Francken.</hi> This fellow in the Seſſion of the Synod of <hi>Chmelnica,</hi> deſiring to ſhew a proof of his learning and wit, did in a more arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant manner then was meet, challenge thoſe Paſtors to diſpute, ſlighting the mean learning of every one. And that he might with very plenty puzzle and overwhelm him that was to diſpute, having before-hand provided himſelf, he together propoſed fifty agruments againſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration of Chriſt. This matter troubled ſome, and they, though the Church had ſo often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected <hi>Socinus,</hi> did yet enjoyne him to make an
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115484:17"/>
anſwer. He attentively hearing the man, who had on a ſudden entered upon an unjuſt way of arguing, and did with one breath almoſt, pour out ſo many prepared ſhafts, was admoniſhed to take in writing at leaſt the heads of the reaſons to which an anſwer was to be returned. But he in confidence of his memory, ſlighted the aſſiſtance of his pen, and patiently heard the man utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe reaſons of his as long as he pleaſed; and by and by in the ſame order repeating the long ſeries of his arguments, gave ſuch a ſolid anſwer to each of them, that the Adverſary had hardly any thing to mutter againſt him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon having profeſſed that he was unskilled and unprepared, he went away confounded, to the admiration of all. And becauſe we have touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the endowments of his nature, if any man be curious to know the figure of his body alſo, let him know that he wanted not a form anſwerable to his diſpoſition, being of ſuch a ſtature as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not the juſt ſize, yet was neerer to tallneſs. The habit of his body was ſomewhat ſlender, yet within meaſure. In his countenance the dignity of his high forhead, and Maſculine beauty of his eyes did caſt a glance. Nor did the comlineſs and grace of his look diminiſh the vigor and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty thereof. He was ſomewhat ſparing of meat and ſleep, and abſtinent of all pleaſures without affectation, only in the conſervation of his health he ſeemed ſcrupulous, and oftentimes over-dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. Yet was he for the moſt part of a proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous health, but that he was ſometimes troubled with the pains of the ſtone, and with the colick. Moreover, being grown ſomewhat old, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of the dimneſs of his ſight, contracted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115484:17"/>
with overmuch watching. The genius of his life was gentle and innocent. There was a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſimplicity in his maners, which was ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered with gravity, that he was free from all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perciliouſneſs. Whence it came to paſs that you would ſooner reverence him then you could fear him. He was very affable, giving honor to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one exceedingly; and would you deſire to reprove any thing in him, there was nothing neerer to diſcommendation, then the over-much debaſement of himſelf.</p>
                  <p>The clothing of his body was modeſt, but yet neat and ſpruce; and though he was at a remote diſtance from bravery, yet was he leſs averſe from ſlight ornaments. He was officious towards his friends, and diligent in all parts of his life. He had ſo won the affection of the Princes, in whoſe ſervice he ſpent part of his life, that neither could long abſence extinguiſh the deſire of him, nor manifeſt offence obliterate the favour to him. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhewed all manner of officiouſneſs towards his Unkles, brethren, and male-kindred, he chiefly regarded and reverenced <hi>Laelius.</hi> Amongſt his female-kindred, beſides his Grandmother <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milla,</hi> a moſt choice Matron, he exceedingly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Aunt <hi>Portia,</hi> and his Siſter <hi>Phyllis,</hi> and that according to their deſerts. The former of which twain, being whileſt ſhe lived, an example of moſt commendable chaſtity, did by her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and incredible gentleneſs of manners ſo gain the affection of her husband <hi>Laelius Beccius,</hi> a man of rank and quality, that he would often ſay with tears that he was unworthy of ſuch and ſo great a wife. The latter by the ſanctity of her maners and diſcipline in governing the houſe, had
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115484:18"/>
ſo approved her ſelf to her husband <hi>Cornelius Marſilius</hi> a great Noble man, that at her death ſhe left behind her an immortal deſire of her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. And foraſmuch as we are long ſince ſlipt from the endowments of nature to thoſe which he acquired by his own induſtry, we muſt not paſs-over in ſilence ſome of his vertues, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he was eminent above many. I cannot eaſily ſay whether there was more fire or wit in ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a diſpoſition, ſo prone to choler had nature framed him, before he had allayed thoſe violent motions with reaſon. Nevertheleſs he did ſo break and tame his cholerick temper, that the mildneſs which afterwards ſhined-forth in him, ſeemed to very many to be the praiſe of nature, not of induſtry. The commendation of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience likewiſe is enhanced as by the indignity of his fortune and injuries, ſo alſo by his delicate and conſequently touchy diſpoſition. No evil is wont to happen unto ſuch perſons without an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite reſentment; nor is it ſo much to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at, that oftentimes a larger wit is capable of more ſorrow.</p>
                  <p>But he in this fight alſo appeared conqueror of his fortune and nature, after he had with a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian greatneſs of mind born and undergone ſo many calamityes from ſtrangers, ſo many inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries from his countrymen, perills from enemies, ingratitude from friends, envy from the learned, hatred from the ignorant, infamy from all, pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from fortune, in fine a continual repulſe, not without ignominy, from that very Church, which he had chiefly beautified. I have almoſt done an injury to fortune, in ſeeming to have aſcribed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her the cauſe of his poverty. But I have not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115484:18"/>
now accuſed her fault, but intimated her condition: which <hi>Socinus</hi> might perhaps by Fortune's means have eſcaped, would either his conſcience or a certain generoſity of mind have permitted him. Certainly he never ſought after the ſame of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by beggery. Nevertheleſs as often as he was able to ſuſtain his condition with the ſmalleſt means, he could not be brought to take ſuch gifts as were freely offered him. Yea he did of his own accord expend his means on the poor. Nor was he only converſant in every kind of alms, but in every kind of liberality alſo: ſo as you may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by underſtand that his charity was enflamed with the promiſcuous love of all men. Likewiſe he publiſhed certain books at his own charges; that he might omit nothing for the accompliſhment of his ardent Zeal to promote Divine Truth, which he had undertaken to propagate, what with ſo many writings, what with ſo many letters, what with ſo many private and publike diſputations, what with ſo many informations of them who were in all places the Interpreters of his mind, what with ſo many long journeys, moſt of them from the utmoſt border of <hi>Sileſia</hi> to the midſt of <hi>Lituania,</hi> what with the loſs of health, fame, and fortunes, what finally with the hazard of his life. That very thing which had been the only ſolace to ſuſtain him in the midſt of ſo great labours and perils, did he continually inculcate to the whole Church, as the only remedy to lead a holy life, namely a continual hope of Immortality, which he thought was to be carefully and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately cheriſhed. So that when a certain old man ſhewed a tomb built for himſelf in token of piety, ſaying that he did perpetually meditate on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115484:19"/>
death<hi>: Socinus</hi> replyed, that he would do more rightly, if he did meditate on the reaſon of the Reſurrection. Certainly his prudence ſhined-forth in all the parts of his life, but chiefly in his judgment of ſpiritual things, and was as it were a certain fruit of his humility and his modeſty, a vertue ſo inbred and peculiar to his nature, that in other vertues he may ſeem to have vyed with others; in this, with himſelf. He never deſpiſed any man; never attempted any thing but with advice and circumſpection. In his very ſtudyes alſo he was ſo far from all ſelf-confidence, that he never aſſayed to write any thing, but what had been concocted with long and mature meditation. And this may eaſily be diſcerned in his works. How often did he go very gingerly through thoſe rough wayes which others would have ſecurely trodden? So that no man ſeemeth to have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſted anothers wit, as he did his own. Which, as we have ſaid, was then the reward, and now the token of his ſingular modeſty. But eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his faith did much ſhine-forth amongſt other praiſes. None in the memory of men was better furniſhed with all helps whereby we aſcend to fame, and wealth, and the higheſt pitch of this life: nature, fortune, and finally induſtry, had emulouſly accumulated nobility of ſtock, ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of friendſhips, grace of Princes, liberal means, health, wit, eloquence, learning, and a natural reach capable of the greateſt matters. Obedience to the call of God, and the pledge of truth entruſted to him, coſt him the loſs of ſo great priviledges. It was a ſmall matter to have forſaken ſo many pledges of the greateſt hope, had he not alſo, as a ſacrifice devoted to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115484:19"/>
publike hatred, wittingly and willingly expoſed himſelf to infinite miſeryes, want, hazards, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mityes, univerſal contempt, reproches, contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes, &amp; to an execrable memory of his name in all places. Nor indeed looked he for anyother reward at preſent, or ſhortly after. His wiſhes reached beyond the bounds of his life, yea beyond the race of the preſent age; and his hope was ſo tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly erected towards heaven, that it reſted on no prop of earthly ſolace. I detract not from the praiſes due to the merits of other men: each of them hath his proper honor. Yet will I by their good leave ſay, that ſome famous men have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps made an attempt at ſo ſublime a proof of faith, but I cannot tell whether any one hath reached it. For the greateſt part wanted not helps whereby their vertue was ſoon relieved, ſo that they were not long God's creditors. The magnanimity of <hi>Luther</hi> and others was quickly entertained with the applauſe and affections of Princes and peoples. How many others, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe poor and obſcure, were by the maintenance of God's cauſe advanced to riches and power? whom nevertheleſs this viciſſitude doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from the praiſe of faith, if that which was the cauſe of their advancement, did grow up to maturity together with them.</p>
                  <p>But they cannot eaſily be admitted into this number, who even with the great detriment of their eſtates eſpouſe the cauſe of God (whether truly ſuch, or pretended) being now in a flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition, and come to maturity. For they have what to hope-for on the earth, even with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect to heaven; and in the expectation of ſuch preſent rewards you cannot alwayes ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115484:20"/>
diſcern, whether they repoſe greater confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God, then in their own induſtry.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Laelius</hi> and <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> men of ſo great judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo great knowledge and experience of the age wherein they lived, what ſolace could they promiſe themſelves in the earth whileſt they lived, yea in the next enſuing age, for ſo many labours and dangers, having profeſſed ſuch te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets as were ſet-off with no pomp of authority, no engagement of parties, no connivency at a more diſſolute life, yea no other blandiſhment whatſoever; but were rather diſtaſtful and odious unto all by reaſon of their auſterity? Certainly I can here eſpy no crevice of earthly hope, which may detract a whit from the praiſe of a moſt noble faith, which how great ſoever it was, being excluded out of all the earth, was mounted up to heaven, and there converſed with the clemency of God alone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ignatius</hi> alſo, that I may omit others, in the memory of our fathers, contemned his countrey, kindred, wealth, honors, and other allurements, and alſo underwent many labours and dangers of his own accord, having profeſſed a zeal to Gods glory, and the warfare of faith. I ſlight not the greatneſs of mind, which ſhewed it ſelf in him or ſome like to him. For neither did they haſten unto glory through ſuch a way as was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſant. Nevertheleſs I do not yet here behold that difficult proof of a more noble faith, which we ſeek for. I aſſume not ſo much to my ſelf, nor is it at preſent very material, as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſentence concerning the purpoſe of any ones mind, which will at length be performed by an infallible Judge. Wherefore I regard not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115484:20"/>
what <hi>Ignatius</hi> had in his mind, ſince for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent buſineſs it is ſufficient, what he might have. Tis true, he ſaw the Popes affaires in ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces afflicted, but could not be ignorant, that in moſt, or at leaſt in the more powerful ones, and conſequently in his countrey, and where he intended to fix his abode, they were well eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and flouriſhing. Who would affirm that the immenſe rewards, which that Church pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently repayeth to her defenders, were unknown to <hi>Ignatius?</hi> Certainly the ſpur of glory is very ſharp in generous minds. Whereſoever an illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious field of glory is opened, not only plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and riches become ſordid in compariſon thereof, but very life it ſelf is vilifyed. And therefore even Martyrdomes are eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone for a proſperous and rich Church, without a more noble proof of religious faith, nor conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently can they deſerve more admiration, then thoſe brave Lads of <hi>Canna</hi> and <hi>Trebia,</hi> who were born for the <hi>Punick</hi> times; or if you like not the common ſouldiery, then <hi>Codrus,</hi> who feared not to dye for his countrey. Indeed whoſoever hath ſought after Eternity of name in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> did wiſely chuſe a race for his glory. For the <hi>Roman,</hi> Commonwealth heretofore (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhe grew great by this means chiefly) did never propoſe ſo many and ſo great rewards to dangers undertaken for her ſake, as the <hi>Roman</hi> Church doth hold-forth. For thoſe ſumptuous beds and altars were a late inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Commonwealth, and that to gratifie the Emperors only. Whereas the Church doth confer upon her benefactors not onely everlaſting veneration of name, but alſo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115484:21"/>
temples, and Orders, and an honorable place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the canonized Saints. What higher thing can the moſt ardent thirſt of glory aſpire unto? Wherefore when ſo large offer's are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and almoſt graſped with the hand, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, though with ſome loſs of his eſtate, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into that warfare, hath no great reaſon to boaſt of his faith before God. Whileſt the Riches of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, the power of ſo many Princes, and the hugeneſs of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Empire diſperſed over the world came-in to his aid, it was an eaſie matter even in the greateſt danger to run before the Enſignes. That was an eſſay of a humane and military fortitude, not riſing up to the more ſacred glory of the Martyrs or Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Primitive Church. For they did ſo ſincerely mind heaven, that they had nothing left them to be hoped-for in the earth. After their example <hi>Laelius</hi> and <hi>Fauſtus</hi> did ſo truſt God with thoſe things which they loſt for his ſake, that they received hardly any earthly pledges of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to come, no humane ſecurity for the Divine Hope, no ſolace. They followed the faith and clemency of God alone, in expectation to receive the ſame a long time after their deceaſe. And having been through the courſe of their lives per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually deſpiſed, and inglorious, and only fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for the hatred conceived againſt them, they did not ſo much as at their death receive a taſt of a more honorable report. Nevertheleſs the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficence of the moſt faithful God did never turn bankrupt to any one that had truſted him. Nor would he have that noble paire of his ſervants be buryed in perpetual oblivion, but ſhewed them to the world on that ſide of them where they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115484:21"/>
might be gloriouſly known, having brought to light ſo many famous monuments of their wits.</p>
                  <p>And although the full wages of their warfare conſiſted not in this reward, yet nevertheleſs he hath begun ſo bountifully to aſſert the very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of their name amongſt men, that it is perhaps more to be feared leſt poſterity ſhould confer on them too-much dignity, then none at all.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115484:22"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:115484:22"/>
An Excellent DISCOURSE Which the ſame POLONIAN Knight Would have had Premiſed TO THE WORKS OF SOCINUS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Moone,</hi> at the ſeven Stars in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, neer the great North-doore. 1653.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115484:23"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115484:23"/>
                  <head>AN Excellent Diſcourſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE wit of man was hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore much turmoiled in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-out the way of Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: but no contention, no induſtry of mortals could find out that, for which we ought to be indebted meerly to the favour of the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal God. Wherefore a great part of Mankind was enveigled with the fawning allurements of pleaſure. Nor were fewer overcome with the gliſtering of Gold, and enſlaved with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of riches. Certainly on this lime-twig al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the rabble of mortals have ſticked; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the more noble Wits did juſtly condemne ſo bad and ſordid an image of Happineſs. They therefore thought Glory, Empire, Power, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like things, to be more worthy of that height. But the wiſer ſort of men did very juſtly deſpiſe theſe vain and fleeting Gifts of fortune alſo. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thoſe things which are at firſt the blandiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115484:24"/>
and afterwards the ſpoils of this tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory life, as beauty and ſtrength of body, happy marriage, numerous off-ſpring, and the vivacity of a long old age, ſeemed lyable to the ſame diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain with the former things. There remained the honor and integrity of a life guided by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, wherein the beſt of men placed the top of our felicity. And I ingenuouſly confeſs that there is nothing amongſt humane matters which riſeth up higher and neerer to that pitch: but how our mind ſhould reſt there, I cannot yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern. For if you remove the other ſolaces and contentments of humane life, I ſee no other fruit in vertue worthy of felicity, then that of a good conſcience. Nor indeed do I think that that joy of the mind congratulating it ſelf is to be ſlighted. But how it is able to ſecure us from the incident miſeries that do infeſt the life of man, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll-up the numbers of juſt happineſs, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not apprehend. For our mind, in the felicity which it ſueth after, doth not only ſeek the ſolace, but vacuity of evils; nor deſire to be happyer then the moſt miſerable, but to be void of all miſery. For not to call them evils and miſeries, which are irkſome to the body or life of man, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth of a proud ſtile, and ſuch as thwarteth humane capacity. Let us leave it to <hi>Homer,</hi> who only durſt to ſpeak in the language of the Gods, and that of right, inaſmuch as he was not a Painter, but a Poet.</p>
                  <p>Men (ſaith he touching a certain bird) call it <hi>Chal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is,</hi> the Gods <hi>Cymindis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We, as long as we are lyable to the caſualties
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115484:24"/>
of body and fortune, will be enforced to impoſe the names of good and evil, rather according to the ſenſe of Humanity, then ſuitably to the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of Philoſophy. Wherefore we are of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that calamitous vertue falleth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of happineſs, and that a conſcience of good works, though worthy of proſperity, is yet oftentimes neerer to pity, then envy. Nor was this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the more acute Philoſophers, who not content to have placed happineſs in the action of vertue, added the condition of a proſperous life and of outward goods. Upon which account thoſe prime men are undeſervedly traduced. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more ridiculous, then to circumſcribe the reaſon of happineſs, which conſiſteth in the ſolid affluence of things, within the limits of a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but naked and barren cogitation. By this accoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Felicity is poor and needy, if vertue ſerve her at her own charges, nor hath other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of dangers, then the remembrance of them. Nevertheleſs I do not conceive that her chief re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is proſperity and ſucceſs in this life; nor imagine that the Prince of Philoſophers thought ſo. Howbeit it is a wretched condition, and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of vertue, that ſhe being innocent ſhould be puniſhed with great misfortunes, or having very well deſerved, be lurched of the chief, yea neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary commodities and comforts of life. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was fitting, that that, whatſoever it be, without which the life of men is bitter and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitous, ſhould be annexed to that happineſs, to which we aſcend by vertue. Neither again with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ground was this kind of happineſs diſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ked. For if it conſiſteth not without outward proſperity, which can neither be at firſt gotten, nor aftewards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115484:25"/>
at our pleaſure, what hope or ſtreſs is to be placed therein, ſince it cannot happen to us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our endeavour, and may be taken from us againſt our will?</p>
                  <p>Howbeit you may more juſtly here bewail the condition of our mortality, then reprove the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the moſt acute philoſopher. He did what he was able, and drew the lineaments of happneſs, how great ſoever might heretofore be hoped-for in this life. What is he to blame, if it be not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable by every ones induſtry? If there be ſomething in it, which you ſuppoſe to be neither firm, nor ſtable? In ſhort, if it do not ſatiate the greedineſs of mans mind? For whatſoever that felicity was, which might be hoped for in this life, it laboured with great and manifold defect. For firſt, in that there was no paſſage to it, but by vertue, and it had not a certain reward, and ſuch as was worthy of it, thoſe complexions that were unhappily diſpoſed by nature, were quite excluded therefrom. And for the ſame cauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven nobler diſpoſitions could not aſpire to the higheſt pitch of vertue. Again, if any man had by a more happy genius arrived through much difficulty to ſome praiſe of vertue, Good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, which was no leſs a deaf then blind God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs, was to be entreated, that ſhe would either become, or remain propitious: without whoſe moſt uncertain help none could by meer vertue maintain the ſtate of his happineſs. Finally, though ſome man were ſo highly favoured both by Vertue and Fortune, that they conſpired to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to make him happy even unto envy, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he could not be void of trepidation whilſt an inevitable neceſſity of dying hung over his head. Which was ſo far from being mitigated
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115484:25"/>
with the ſolace of the felicity which he enjoyed, that the more happily a man lived, the more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing was he to depart from his happineſs: and in the greater affluence of good things, he had the juſter cauſe of fear and ſorrow. How hard therefore was the condition of mortality, which though advanced to ſo rare a ſtate as few could wiſh-for, was notwithſtanding unſecure from ſo great ſorrow and anxiety! To finde an iſſue of theſe evils and miſeries, and ſo tend directly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſincere happineſs, did (as we before hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) exceed the power of man. That glory was reſerved for the bounty of the Moſt high God, who only by his Son diſcovered that Secret of Eternity, <hi>that there was a reward worthy of vertue beſides it ſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He firſt by exceeding-great promiſes erected the deſires of men to true Happineſs; and gave not only the pleaſing overture of ſo incredible a wiſh, but the undoubted pledges of the hope it ſelf. We have the Son for an hoſtage of the Father's faithfulneſs, the purity and holineſs of whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine doth ſufficiently plead for it ſelf without Advocates and Patronage: whoſe innocency of life confirms his Doctrine; whoſe ſtupendious miracles, aſſert not only his Doctrine but his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency alſo. Whoſe death as undergone for the teſtimony of his Doctrine, argueth his ſincerity; as overcome, ſheweth the truth of his undoubted teſtimony. Whoſe reſurrection from death ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth before our eyes a pattern of his ſublime pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; whoſe exaltation and empire ſhew the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude thereof. In a word, are the things which he performed by the Apoſtles, and the admirable operations of the Holy Spirit, who without arms
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115484:26"/>
ſubdued the armed world, and without blandiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments allured ſo many nations to the hardſhip of vertue, to be eſteemed ſlight proofs both of his Divine Empire, and our hope? Is it credible that any men would heretofore in this world have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone a huge deal of pains not only without any reward, but with apparent ruine, had they not been emboldened with a hope of ſomething after this life? Could even a ſtrong faith, whileſt the memory of things was yet freſh, afford ſo great a proof of it ſelf, had there been any ſolid or juſt ground of diſtruſt? Wherefore the firſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt was to draw the whole world to the belief of thoſe things, which a few very ſimple men had in the beginning ſeen with their eyes. So many cities and empires, ſo many nations and peoples, ſo many Iles and utmoſt borders of the earth, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in other things for the moſt part at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance amongſt themſelves, do yet agree in the belief of thoſe things, which the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion holdeth forth. How happy was mankind, which having been before drowned in profound darkneſs, was ſuddenly environed with ſo great a light! How bleſſed was the condition of men, to whom the way of heaven and immortality was not only ſhewn in a friendly manner, but levelled and prepared for them! This is that true felicity which lyeth open unto every one that ſeriouſly deſires it, and cannot be taken away from a man againſt his will. Neither fortune, nor the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous neceſſity of fate, nor the ſilly diſtaff of the deſtinies, hath any power over it. As for the right which God himſelf had over it, he hath reſigned the ſame up to thoſe, who believe his promiſes in Chriſt, and remember the covenant,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115484:26"/>
which he hath made with us, whom he bought with the precious blood of his Son. In the laſt place, whatſoever things did heretofore diſturb or delay the proſperity of men in this life, are removed far away from this happineſs. So great rewards are in it propoſed unto vertue, that all men have an acceſs to the top thereof: ſo great helps and ſupports are added, that neither an untoward diſpoſition, nor bad education, nor dulneſs of wit, nor ignorance of learning, nor weakneſs of ſex, nor meanneſs of birth, nor po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, nor employment of life, nor any other thing, but voluntary wickedneſs, can hinder a man from enjoying it. After that the Chriſtian Religion had drenched ſo many nations in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly cares, no longer was vertue ſuppliant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fortune, that ſhe would not diſturb her courſe with ſad diſaſters, nor interrupt her ſolid joyes with humane terrors and lamentations. Then did ſhe begin to deſpiſe that blind God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs without pride, and provoke her without raſhneſs, being as ſecure of her own ſafety as of victory. For God would not ſuffer fortune to have greater power over vertue in this preſent life, then ſuited with the indulgence of a kind father towards his children. And though her threatened blows be not diſappointed, yet i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it ſerviceable to our glory and the encreaſe of our happineſs, when having ſurmounted all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we enjoy the glad and glorious memory of our labours. In ſhort, that very invincible ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of dying, which waiting on the rear of our life, did blaſt its accumulated joyes, afar off with terror, and neer at hand with ſad deſtruction, hath long ſince ſubmitted her conquered neck to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115484:27"/>
vertue and faith. Nor is it an impeachment here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, that this enemy ſeemeth not as yet to have caſt away his weapons, for his chiefeſt blade is dulled, in that death was long ſince weakened by the reſurrection of Chriſt. O happy and more then <hi>Saturnian</hi> age, wherein ſo pleaſing a glance did firſt ſhine-forth to the world! It was an eaſie thing for mankind in ſo ſaving a light to paſs roundly on to immortality, but I know not by what injury of viciſſitude, they could not long ſincerely enjoy ſo great a happineſs. Whether it were ſome malignant Spirit, or the very world it ſelf envyed her own fortune, or finally the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of almighty God, that vertue might never want a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>fficient combate, certain it is that the hope of ſo happy a condition, together with the way thereunto, hath been for many ages involved with the greateſt difficulties. For firſt, the very confidence of our hope (which onely is able to ſet us on the top of true happineſs) began to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermined and ſhaken with engines well-nigh planted againſt it. Next, the very Religion of Chriſt, which alone gave aſſurance of ſo great a hope to mankind, was on ſeveral accounts called into queſtion. Finally, a great impediment lay in the way to hinder us not only from conceiving, but alſo venturing on this hope. And (which would moſt of all move you with grief and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation) all theſe things were done by them, who profeſſed themſelves competitors of the felicity hoped for.</p>
                  <p>For, that we may return unto what was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the firſt place, what engine was fitter to undermine our faith, then the difficulty of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to life? That life might perhaps be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115484:27"/>
to a very great length, would though with ſome difficulty be aſſented unto by reaſon, but that being once taken away it ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored again for ever, was, though not contrary to reaſon, yet above belief. In ſo great a miracle, thwarting the cuſtome of nature, mankind could hardly believe without an example. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God expoſed to the view of all a certain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment thereof, having recalled him to life, who did not at all exceed others as to the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mortal nature. This ſo evident a prop of our faith is taken from us by the common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Chriſtians: if <hi>Jeſus</hi> that was raiſed from the dead be the very moſt high God, not differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in eſſence from the Father. For neither did he really dye (for who would imagine that the Supreme Power can dye? who would affirm that a perſon coeternal and coeſſential with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was killed?) nor when he was dead, did he, like us, ſtand in need of anothers help: ſo that returning unto life in a glorious manner, he did by his own ſtrength, and ſuch a power, as was neither taken away from him, nor laid down by him, reſcue himſelf out of the jaws of death. Tell me now, what is there in us like hereunto? It is not ſomething added unto us, but we our ſelves that dye; and what hope is there in our ſtrength, being altogether broken and quelled by death? Certainly the Ghoſts or perſons of the dead do not watch an opportunity to raiſe themſelves by their own power out of ſo profound a ſleep. Moreover, as if it had been a ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to have our faith ſo dangerouſly ſhaken in a thing of the greateſt moment, a very provident care was alſo taken, that it might not make uſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115484:28"/>
of ſome other means to erect it ſelf. For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it was the chief duty of a lively faith ſincerely to believe ſo ſublime promiſes of God; the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Chriſtians was made to believe, that the main buſineſs of faith was to believe certain opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions touching the nature of God, and other the like doctrines. Thus did the Publick error wreſt and turn aſide the minds of all from the true exerciſe of faith, to the affectation of vain opinions. Whereby it came to paſs that all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted concerning the nature of God, but few be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved his promiſes, and accordingly not many obeyed his commandments. So that with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle adoe faith degenerated into opinion, religion into Philoſophy, vertue into contemplation, zeal into contention, love into faction. Nor could it be otherwiſe, when once the maners of men were ſlighted, and their wits only began to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and examined.</p>
                  <p>I come now to the ſecond engine wherewith our faith was ſhaken, and which ſtrook at our hope through the ſide of our whole rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gion. No ſect, no religion, beſides the Chriſtian doth ſolidly promiſe heaven and the ſtars to them who have well deſerved. The pledge of ſo great a promiſe periſheth, if the promiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> himſelf is called into queſtion. But they have taken the direct way to make it be condemned of falſhood, or burthened with a very juſt ground of ſuſpicion, who deem ſuch doctrines fundamental thereunto, as are falſe and repugnant to all reaſon. Who would not fall a weeping for the miſeryes of the Church, when he conſidereth how much ſhe hath degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from her primitive chaſtity? And in the midſt of grief a juſt indignation ſometimes break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth-out,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115484:28"/>
to ſee that thoſe ancient Biſhops ſhould in the doctrine touching God not be aſhamed violently to draw the ſenſe of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to the opinions of the <hi>Greek</hi> (ſhall I ſay?) or <hi>Barbarous</hi> Philoſophy. The ancient Church heretofore laughed at the Gnoſticks, for corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting prophane Philoſophy with ſhreds taken out of the Chriſtian doctrine, and prodigiouſly patch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together. When in the mean ſhe her ſelf (forſooth) making a more ſober uſe of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, had rather ſeem to have defiled the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Divinity, then the Learning of that age. Did thoſe Fathers think it ſo miſerable a thing, to be accounted ignorant of thoſe arts, which were then ſo ardently affected by the times? But as they, who deſire to ſit on two ſtools, fall from b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th, even ſo thoſe Biſhops did neither ſincerely retain the primitive ſimplicity of the Sacred Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, nor the conjectures of prophane wits. Whereupon the Doctrines of the Church were ſtuffed with abſurd and contradictions opinions; which, inaſmuch they pull-up by the roots the notions naturally implanted in us, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently reaſon it ſelf, are obtruded under the pretence of Faith.</p>
                  <p>Which might notwithſtanding be endured, firſt if they onely ſurpaſſed the power of our mind, and did not overthrow it. For there is a wide difference between nor perceiving the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a thing, and ſeeing the falſhood thereof. Becauſe the truth is oftentimes ſo deeply hid, that it can hardly be brought to light; whereas falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood can ſeldome lye ſo cloſe, but that it may be traced out. Wherefore I could wiſh that it were as eaſie a matter to cure ignorance, as to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115484:29"/>
convince errors of falſhood. Otherwiſe to what purpoſe doth our mind ſerve, if it ſhall on any pretence be afraid to condemne that, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth a contradiction? Furthermore, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe of paradoxes under the buckler of Faith might be endured, did men in very deed fly from the examination of Reaſon, to the authority of Divine Teſtimony. But when the cauſe begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to ſink under the judgement of Reaſon, a ſudden ſupply is fetched from Sacred Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. When this very Revelation cometh to ſcanning, we find it (as we formerly hinted) to be more evidently diſcovered by Platonick Wits, then by the Apoſtolick Writers. Again, if there be any place in the Holy Oracles, which may ſeem to prove it, it is ſo obſcure, that we muſt again return to thoſe flying and aiery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations of mans brain, to have ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty concerning the ambiguous ſenſe thereof. In framing which conſequences, if the cauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin again to totter, a ridiculous return is alſo made again to the belief of the Heavenly Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, as to a known ſtarting-hole. As if it had been long ſince granted, that this were a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine delivered by God, and not the very Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine it ſelf were then moſt called into queſtion. By this means whileſt Uncertain Reaſon fetcheth unſeaſonable help from Suſpected Revelation, &amp; Suſpected Revelation from Uncertain Reaſon, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them is found to have any ſtability. Laſt of all, there are in the Scriptures ſo many and ſo clear teſtimonies of the contrary opinion, that neither can thoſe paradoxes conſiſt with the ſafety of them, nor the authority of Holy writ remain ſafe, if they be called into queſtion. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115484:29"/>
no Chriſtian dares to make a ſcruple con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning either the certainty or ſenſe of thoſe teſtimonies: only it is urged that they are mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and defective, and conſequently have need of ſomething added to them from abroad for the full knowledge of Divine things. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed let us herein grant their requeſt, ſo that they abuſe not this liberty of adding, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thoſe things which they promiſed to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. But what if they produce ſuch additions, as quite overthrow the certainty and reaſon of thoſe things, to which they are added? This certainly is not to be endured, inaſmuch as they had promiſed to ſupply our teſtimonies, and not to aboliſh them.</p>
                  <p>But they fetch thoſe ſupplements out of the Sacred Oracles, by whoſe rule they would have their other teſtimonies tryed. Truly we deny not that the Scripture is the moſt faithful inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter of it ſelf. But firſt we muſt conſider, with what fidelity they draw that from ſome places of the Scripture, which is repugnant to the open ſenſe thereof elſewhere. Next we muſt demand of them, with what forehead they require that thoſe places, concerning whoſe meaning (by reaſon of the open evidence) they do in a manner agree with the Adverſaryes, ſhould be explained by others, concerning whoſe expoſition there is the greateſt controverſie. What perverſe and prepoſterous order of knowledge is that, to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate the light by darkneſs? As if this were the way to perceive the moſt known things, even to be blind in ſuch as are unknown. How great ſupport therefore in the Divine Oracles thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions have, which are otherwiſe repugnant
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115484:30"/>
unto reaſon, and how juſtly they implore the help of Faith is evident from thoſe things which we have diſcourſed. But to what purpoſe is all this, if notwithſtanding the greateſt part of men are perſwaded, that it very much concerneth the Chriſtian Religion, that ſo incredible things be believed? Neither is this the only point, wherein the truth of ſo Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Faith is traduced. What ſhould I here mention that ſink of moſt filthy errors, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the moſt pure doctrine of the Goſpel hath been over-flowed? There was heretofore none ſo profane an opinion, none ſo ſilly a dotage, none ſo ridiculous a ſuperſtition, which (by the great injuſtice of men) did not only find place therein, but alſo eſteem. I omit the portentous opinions touching Tranſubſtantiation, touching the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Power of the Prieſts and the Pope, and touching the worſhip of Images; I omit the fables fetched out of the Academy, touching Limbus, and Purgatory; I omit ſo many bug-bear-apparitions, ſo many marts of abſolutions, and ſales of ſins, ſo many ſtrange rites and forren ceremonies; and ſundry other things, which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Greek alſo, or the Latin Church only hath not bluſhed ſo long to propoſe for the main pillars of the Faith. For whatſoever, either ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrent from all reaſon, or repugnant to the Holy Scripture, hath for ſo many ages been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded on the Generality of Chriſtians, all that hath redounded to the diſgrace of our Religion and Faith, ſince neither could the inbred light of our mind be extinguiſhed by any means, nor the authority of the Scripture be overthrown as long as our Faith remained ſafe. But let that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115484:30"/>
paſs for the deplorable calamity of the world faln in barbariſm; now that the light of a happier age is riſen, and the world beginneth to come out of that thick darkneſs, it is a great indignity that being now awakened and ſtirring it ſhould again be pothered in the ſame or a worſe fogge. For whereunto tendeth the unavoidable condition of Divine Deſtination? whereunto, the moſt unjuſt neceſſity of Fate, far more ſilly and barbarous then the dreams of the Ancients? which doth not preſcribe ſuch a law of life as is equal and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon unto all, but a fixed decree concerning the inmutable ſtate of every particular man; which finally thinketh this only worthy of immenſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, or direful torments, that men, though they be never ſo willing, are not able to reſiſt the will of God. Whereunto, I ſay, tendeth ſo cruel and ſiniſter an opinion, but to enwrap in fable darkeneſs the reaſon both of Gods Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and Man's Obedience? What alſo mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that peculiar opinion of ſome touching the pravity of good works? or that other more common opinion touching our propriety and poſſeſſion of anothers holineſs? Beſides the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our mind, are we not averted from the ſtudy of true piety by the ſtrange mixture of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant things? if when we do never ſo well we are frighted with the conſcience of our good deeds, and when we live never ſo ill we have the confidence of anothers merit? What ſhould I commemorate the price properly paid for our free impunity? and that it is enjoyned us by the law of a moſt equal ſeverity to do impoſſibilities? and that the will, that is, the freedome of man, is ſervile? All theſe opinions can no more be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115484:31"/>
with a ſincere endeavour to live piouſly, then with themſelves. For who would, with the loſs of thoſe things that are moſt dear to him, ſeek to attain ſuch a reward, as he thinketh to be already purchaſed at anothers coſt, and without any pains of his? who would preſs towards a place through rough and craggy wayes, when in the mean time he is perſwaded not only that he cannot get thither, but alſo cannot ſo much as will to go? I know I have touched thoſe points of the Reformed Doctrine (as they call it) which like the ulcers of a moſt delicate part cannot be handled without an exquiſite ſenſe of pain. Wherefore I will add no more; for neither can thoſe things be comprehended in a compendium of words, whoſe number cannot eaſily be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in the mind. Beſides, I know right well that ſome one, having read thoſe few words, will fly-out, and chaſe, as if he were pricked on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: although I endeavour ſo to moderate my ſtile, that none may juſtly take offence. For the Chriſtian world ſleepeth quietly in his ſins, being bolſtered up with thoſe opinions; ſo that if any one attempt to draw away the pillow from his delicate neck, the inflamed faction of Divines falls preſently a raging worſe then a tyger rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of her whelps, and crying-out that Faith and Religion lye at ſtake; when in the mean time onely the private credit of certain men, or the publike allurement of ſinning is brought into danger. They impute this zeal to the honour and glory of God and Chriſt; as if God and Chriſt liked ſuch Doctrines, as utterly root out of the minds of men the true worſhip and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of his Divine Majeſty, conſiſting in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115484:31"/>
Every one thinketh that he ought to endeavour according to his ability, that no low opinion creep in concerning the Eſſence, Perſon, Benefit, and in a word, the Glory of God and Chriſt. Nor do I therein blame them. But tell me, good Sir, why do you give fair titles to foul vices? Is it your deſire truly and magnificently to aſſert the glory of God? then uſe all diſigence that the light of your vertues may ſhine before all men. Which that you may the more readily perform, diſcard all portentous opinions, that may hinder you in the courſe of true piety. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you uſe ſuch induſtry about Divine Things, you muſt of neceſſity be very ignorant of them. For it is a moſt vain hope of yours, to think to win the favour of God and Chriſt by flattery, whereas it is to be acquired only by obedience. Chriſt will ſcorn blandiſhmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s and titles, which have been hitherto a cloke for the diſobedience of his commandments. A ſaving light ſhined-forth to the world: but men rather loved dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, becauſe they are enamoured on their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Wickedneſs. What wonder therefore is it, that doctrines ſo abſurd, ſo contradictious, ſo diſtant and abhorrent from all reaſon have been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded on their heedleſs mindes? All thoſe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets crept on them in the diſmal time of night and darkneſs, whileſt men buried in the ſweet ſleep of their ſins, obſerve not the blind and ſecret ſnares laid for them. But above all, as we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly hinted, the credit of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was impeached, when once men began to be perſwaded, that it could not ſtand without ſuch rotten and weak props. Which are juſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt, not only for ſuſpicion of moſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115484:32"/>
evident falſhood, but alſo becauſe they pull the ſtock of vertue out of the hearts of men by the very roots, whereas our mind, though ſhe turn her ſelf every way, is never able to condemne ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as alſo other common notions. Thus our Religion being called into queſtion by means of ſo many inextricable wayes of error, how ſmall a number is there even of Chriſtians (that I may not ſpeak of others) that hath been able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the confidence of their hope untouched and unſtained amidſt ſo many and ſo grievous ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions?</p>
                  <p>Hence at length it came to paſs, according to our third propoſal, that after our faith and hope, which only was able to keep us in the obedience of Chriſt had been hindered, the very obedience it ſelf was alſo hindered, and conſequently the ready way to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> felicity hoped-for. For all kinds of crimes and vices brake into the Church in great throngs. The whole body of the Church is full of ſo many corruptions in manners, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſeaſes and ulcers, that it is a tedious work to proſecute every one in particular. Innumerable errors produced infinite abuſes. Wherefore, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the reſt, which raign everywhere to the infamy of Religion, I will commemorate but twain, whereof not only the impurity was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but the impiety alſo was enjoyned. For firſt of all, the worſhip of the Supreme Power being turned aſide from a ſpiritual and heavenly maner, to ugly rites and ceremonies, a ſad and ſhameful kind of Idolatry was introduced. And as if there were a danger, leſt men, if not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thereunto, ſhould more timerouſly trample under foot the expreſs commandments
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115484:32"/>
of God, by the publick ſanctions and decrees of the Church it was almoſt in very terms enjoyned, that the firſt and chiefeſt precept of God ſhould be violated, and the ſecond be expunged out of the number of the other ten.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, that New and Royal Law of Chriſt, which amongſt others hath the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, not onely as the complement and top of perfection, but as the ordinary badge of his peculiar people, the Law, I ſay, of Love was publickly abrogated by the vileſt cuſtomes and inſtitutions. I omit other things, which are practiſed to the prejudice thereof, not by clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtine infirmity, or private attempt, but by publick Advice. That one thing is ſufficient, which hath for many ages, to the ſhameful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit of the Churches of Chriſt, been a recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved practiſe; namely that thoſe men, who have entruſted themſelves their hopes and fortunes to Jeſus of Nazareth, acknowledged to be the Chriſt of God, and who are reckoned in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and liſted in his ſervice, and whom none (who thinketh not himſelf exempted from the Laws of Chriſt) may ſo much as hate, ſhould notwithſtanding on no other ground, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they diſſent in ſomething, be by their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſervants and ſouldiers not only abuſed with moſt bitter hatred, diſgraces, and injuries, but alſo killed with exquiſite tortures, and with cruel and horrid kinds of puniſhment, This is not a ſpot of private cruelty<hi>:</hi> ſo dire and deteſtable acts as theſe are perpetrated in the name of the Church. For many ages ſince, amongſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt, a prophane and cruel faction hath prevailed, which making havock of the Church
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115484:33"/>
of Chriſt with fire and ſword, doth notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arrogate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o her ſelf the name of the Church, excluding others from the participation thereof. This is ſhe, which hath by the ſlaughter and wounds of the innocent moſt infamouſly polluted her ſelf with blood; this is ſhe, which hath by ſo many doleful fires and diſmal flames, branded her ſelf with this indeleble mark, with theſe prints, to her everlaſting infamy; this is ſhe, who quak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſliding no leſs in the durt of vices, then in the blood of the innocent, is by the Ghoſts of the oppreſſed drawn to the tribunal of the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Judge; In fine, this is the faction, which impoſed ſuch a Prince on the Commonwealth and the Church, whoſe power lately reſting on the lap of Europe, made the Chriſtian world grone, and now puts it in a fright leſt it ſhould reſt upon 't the ſecond time. For the moſt merciful God taking pity on the hardſhip where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we were oppreſſed, did caſt this yoke from off our necks. And now the darkneſs of baſe ſervitude being diſpelled, a moſt pleaſant light of liberty ſhined-forth, when on the ſudden tempeſtuous clouds ariſing threaten a more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal night then the former. What is it, but our ingratitude, that uſually cauſeth God to repent of his benefits? Before the riſing of the light, he ſent the pleaſant glimmering of the morning: but we contenting our ſelves with the twilight, have ſhut our eyes againſt the very beams of the Sun, that we might with more modeſty ſin in the dark. He began to reſtore liberty, but we ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſe ſervitude. For the ſame domination that others exerciſed over us, have we ſuffered to be exerciſed over the weaker ſort, to the end
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115484:33"/>
it might plainly appear that we were not ſo much diſpleaſed with our ſervitude, as with our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Why therefore ſhould we accuſe God, for thruſting us again into moſt horrid darkneſs, when we ſo baſely do deſpiſe the light? Why ſhould we complain, that we are again enſlaved to the Pope, when we by a ſhameful kind of vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalage perform homage to ignobler Maſters? If we liſt to become ſervants, there is ſome choice in taking a more honourable maſter. What then? ſhall we invite all to take up the yoke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain which they had heretofore thrown off their necks? At no hand. For though the new ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude be a grief and ſhame to us, yet do we juſtly congratulate the expulſion of Idolatry to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the old Tyranny. We alſo rejoyce that in many other things the feature of the Church is reſtored to her. But above all we acknowledge it for a ſpecial gift of God, that the due authority and reverence of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is vindicated. So that the foundations of a very excellent hope are already laid; it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth, that as we have expelled Idolatry, ſo we reſtore charity, which cannot be done but by the baniſhment not only of cruelty, but alſo of all tyranny and iniquity. And let us uſe the autority &amp; guidance of the Holy Scripture, which we have aſſerted, to chaſe away the relicks of darkneſs, which have hitherto no leſs weakened the hope of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then disfigured the faith and beauty of our Religion. Why do we linger any longer? why do w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> expect the ſharper goads of God to prick us forward? Certainly in this juncture of time, there is ſomething greater then the mouth of man that thunders out. We are not now ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed of our duty by a humane voice, but
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115484:34"/>
by the dreadful rebuke of the Divine Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. God applyeth a ſad but wholeſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to our ſickneſs. Too much felicity had cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted us, and we had openly looſed the reins to our luſts amidſt the blandiſhments of proſperity. Such of us as have not been carryed away with the force of ſin or improbity to a cruel hatred of auſtere truth, have yet by ſome love or fear of earthly things, been detained in their pleaſing errors with ſoft and gentle fetters. The impiety of the former required puniſhment, the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the latter craved help. And therefore Providence diſpenſeth unto both his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per remedy. Such minds as are overwhelmed with vices, pay for their hatred and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the truth, by being again involved in darkneſs. But ſuch hearts as are honeſt, yet bound with a teather of earthly things, are by the Divine Goodneſs ſet at liberty. Certainly it had been better in the midſt of proſperity to have embraced the offer of truth. But the moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful God did herein alſo take care for honeſt hearts, in that he removed the allurements and encumbrances, wherewith they were kept from the knowledge of truth. Wherefore God doth now openly in the view of the world make tryal, with what ſincerity every one of us hath departed from the ſociety of Antichriſt. If either the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy of faction, or love of parties, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther humane conſideration whatſoever hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto detained any in the warfare of Chriſt, they may retire and betake themſelves thither, where there is an offer of greater preſent advantage. But ye that have truſted the Captain of your faith with the pay of your deferred reward, be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115484:34"/>
not diſcouraged in ſo great a ſtorm of adverſe fortune. This is the means whereby God exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeth and tryeth them that are his. Vertue and truth have in all ages been educated with theſe hardſhips, and grown to maturity by theſe try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls. With theſe evils Chriſt himſelf and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, as alſo the Martyrs and Confeſſors of the Primitive Church have conflicted. Finally, with theſe arms the world alwayes rageth againſt good men; by theſe mines the Tyranny of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt hath now many ages ſince crept-in; with ſuch practiſes as theſe, a great part of thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whom ye Idolize, did drive-on furiouſly; by theſe arts were thoſe Councels, which ye as yet adore, upheld and maintained, whileſt in Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods controverſies were decided with violent factions, and autority, and the decrees of Synods ratified by Imperial power, with fines, diſgraces, baniſhments, and at length with blood it ſelf and extreme puniſhments. God would have you taſt the equity and nature of ſuch arts, to the end ye might underſtand, what ye ought to judge of that autority which grew and was eſtabliſhed by the like means and practiſes. Wherefore reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe prophane and juſtly-ſuſpected preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices of ages and autorities, implore the only aid of the Sacred Oracles, and under their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage ſeek both the way of finding-out the truth, and of defending it being found. Only bring ſincere minds, and ſuch as are deſirous of the truth; and ſince the whole truth may in a maner coſt you no more charge and damage, then hitherto a portion of it did, be bold to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it with both your arms, whileſt it is freely offered to you, and without danger. By this
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115484:35"/>
means it will come to paſs, that your hope and faith b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing underſet with better props, will more readily erect it ſelf to the true worſhip and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of God, and abide more conſtantly in the ſame. For facilitating of which work, ye and all the Church are very much beholding to <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> a man ennobled by his parentage, vertue, and the monuments of his wit; and who, when the heat of envy ſhall evaporate together with the ignorance of the age, will be far more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobled amongſt Poſterity. The praiſes of which man it is better to paſs-over in ſilence, then mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to proſecute<hi>:</hi> Eſpecially becauſe they are in ſome meaſure atteſted and blazoned by his Life, perfixed before this Diſcourſe; but abundantly by the iſſue of his ſublime wit, and the genius of his writings. He was the man that ſtretched the ſinnews of his moſt ſharp judgement, to remove from the Church of Chriſt whatſoever he deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed prejudicial either to the Glory of God, or to the dignity of Religion, or finally to the ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of piety. So that the Reader ſhall in his writings find, firſt moſt of thoſe Engines taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, wherewith the hope of that happineſs to which we aſpire, was together with the Honor of Almighty God, undermined. He ſhall find the dignity of our whole Religion maintained, and its reputation vindicated and aſſerted from thoſe abſurd monſtrous opinions, which have a long time cauſed it moſt injuriouſly to be tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced among them that are without. Finally he ſhall find all the impediments taken away, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with men were letted not only from hoping-for, but alſo entering on the inheritance of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Patrimony, and which they being weary of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115484:35"/>
the piety enjoyned, had procured to themſelves. For not only the ſtudy of univerſal ſanctity was extinguiſhed with fawning pernicious opinions, but alſo licence given to manifeſt offences againſt the Law of God, or the deſire of them enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or alſo the neceſſity of them impoſed. Theſe barricadoes being removed, he ſhall finde the way to the utmoſt happineſs of the largeſt wiſh, fitted and prepared by the incredible bounty of God. Which happineſs for many thouſand yeers before the coming of Chriſt mankind had ſtill deſired, but was ſtill ignorant thereof: which the very Obſervers of the Moſaick Law could only ſometimes ſent-out by a very ſlender gheſs, but never openly detect: and which finally having been diſcovered by Chriſt and the Apoſtles, but ſhortly after covered with the thorns of errors ſpringing-up, and hidden with a diſmal vail of darkneſs, is now again detected and reſtored by the mercy of God, who hath cut down the thorny brake of fables, and cauſed the light of the truth to ariſe. For the aſſenting unto which truth ſo bright and ſhining, the whole Chriſtian world had need only to behold it once without prejudice: but ere it will be brought thereunto, it muſt (unleſs I be miſtaken in the temper of the preſent age) be rouzed up with the blood of the innocent, and with new Martyrdomes.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115484:36"/>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115484:36"/>
                  <head>AN ELOGY Of the Writings of SOCINUS Out of BODECHERUS.</head>
                  <p>THe truth is to be acknowledged eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rywhere. For neither doth ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her value from any perſon, but give it to him. Nor can we in this place for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to give this teſtimony unto <hi>Socinus,</hi> where he agreeth with the Orthodox: let the Chriſtian world hear, if it pleaſe. He diſputeth with the thruſt; granteth to the adverſary whatſoever he may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice to the truth, and his cauſe; where the adverſary is to be preſſed, there
<pb facs="tcp:115484:37"/>
he maketh a ſtand, and argueth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; contendeth rather with Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures then with ſuppoſitions; and with reaſons, not with prejudices, as the School of <hi>Calvin</hi> is for the moſt part wont to do; he ſheltereth not himſelf amidſt certain nice captions; he ſeeketh not ſtarting-holes, but hits the very throat of the cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> In him <hi>Atheiſts, Jews, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, Papiſts,</hi> find matter of employment, otherwiſe then in the writings of the <hi>Calviniſts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="catalogue">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115484:37"/>
                  <head>A CATALOGUE OF THE WORKS OF SOCINUS.</head>
                  <p>AN Explication of the former part of the firſt Chapter of <hi>John.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Touching the ſtate of the firſt man before the fall, a Diſputation againſt <hi>Franciſcus Puccius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Touching the Saviour, a diſputation againſt <hi>Jacobus Covetus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Touching the Invocation of Chriſt, a Diſputation againſt <hi>Franciſcus Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:115484:38"/>
Touching the Adoration of Chriſt, a Diſputation againſt <hi>Chrſtianus Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi> together with the Fragments of a larger Anſwer which <hi>Socinus</hi> did provide againſt <hi>Franciſcus Davidis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Touching the Exiſtence of the onely-begotten Son of God, a Diſputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Eraſmus Joannis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Touching the Nature or Eſſence of Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, and alſo touching the Expiation of ſins by him, a Diſputation againſt <hi>Andreas Volanus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Touching the Divinity of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, an Anſwer to <hi>Wuiekus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Animadverſions on the Aſſertions of the <hi>Poſnanian</hi> Colledge touching the Trinune God, againſt the new <hi>Samoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Defenſe of thoſe Animadverſions, againſt <hi>Gabriel Eutropius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>An Anſwer to a book of <hi>Jacobus Palaeologus,</hi> entituled, <hi>A Defenſe of the true Opinion concerning the Civil Magiſtrate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:115484:38"/>
Sacred Lectures, wherein the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Holy Scriptures, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the New Covenant is aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                  <p>Theological Prelections.</p>
                  <p>An Explication of the ſeventh Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Defence of that Explication.</p>
                  <p>An Expoſition of Chriſt's Sermon in the fifth, ſixth, and ſeventh of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Touching the errors of the Goſpellers, or Calviniſts.</p>
                  <p>Touching Juſtification.</p>
                  <p>The Fragments of two writings touching the Nature of Chriſt and the Trinity.</p>
                  <p>Epiſtles written to ſundry friends.</p>
                  <p>Epiſtles written to <hi>Andreas Dudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dithius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sophiſtical Elenchs.</p>
                  <p>A brief Diſcourſe touching the Cauſe of Faith.</p>
                  <p>Touching the Lord's Supper.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:115484:39"/>
Touching Water-baptiſm, whether a Chriſtian may be without it.</p>
                  <p>Touching the Church.</p>
                  <p>An Inſtitution of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>Certain brief Treatiſes touching di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſubjects pertaining to the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:115484:39"/>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                        <p>In Paules Church Yard Att The ⋆ ⋆ ⋆ ⋆ ⋆ ⋆ ⋆</p>
                        <p>Richard <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
